Aymar Embury II Papers
Aymar Embury II Papers
- Projects by Embury
  - Lincoln Tunnel
    - Photographs, photographs of ventilation building and light standard; 2 items (Box 3)
  - Latter Day Saints chapel (Scarsdale, New York), Edward Coe Embury (architect) and Aymar Embury II (consulting architect)
    - Drawings, positive photostat of perspective rendering (Oversize 9)
  - Long Island Lighting (Long Island, New York)
    - Drawings, 1945; perspective drawings in graphite on tracing paper; 2 items (Oversize 9)
  - Lyman residence (Dana Place, Englewood, New Jersey), Stuart Lyman (client)
    - Specifications (Box 3)
  - Magnolia cemetery, office building, Reese Memorial (Augusta, Georgia)
    - Photographs, exterior (5); photograph of painting (1); 6 items (Box 3)
  - Maidstone Club (East Hampton, Long Island, New York), Embury and Lucas (architects); Aymar Embury II (consulting architect)
    - Drawings, 1931-1954; graphite on tracing paper; mix of design development and working drawings; 69 items (Tube 941)
    - Drawings, 1931-1954; graphite on tracing paper design development drawings (29); sepia diazo prints of working drawings (8); blueprint on linen working drawings of existing building by Roger Bullard (8); photostats of drawings (2); color samples (3); 50 items (Tube 942)
    - Photographs, interior; 5 items (Box 3)
  - Marine Parkway bridge (Brooklyn, New York)
    See also Bridges scrapbooks and Miscellaneous scrapbook and for more photographs of this structure.
    - Drawings, reproductions of drawings; 4 items (Oversize 4)
    - Photographs, photograph of bridge (Box 3)
  - McAlpin residence, David McAlpin (client)
    - Photographs, photographs by Ansel Adams of exterior and grounds; 4 items (Box 3)
  - Memorial skating rink (Prospect Park, Brooklyn, New York), Embury and Lucas (architects); Aymar Embury II (consulting architect)
    - Brochure, hardbound brochure produced by the City of New York Department of Parks (Oversize 9)
  - Metropolitan Museum, addition (New York, New York)
    See also Miscellaneous scrapbook for more images of this building.
    - Drawings, photostats of drawings of west elevation; 2 items (Box 3)
  - Mid-Pines Country Club (Knollwood, North Carolina)
    - Drawings, prints of drawings; 4 items (Box 3)
    - Photographs, exterior (4); interior (2); construction photographs (7); exterior of cabin (4); and photographic excerpt from Architectural Forum; 18 items (Box 3)
  - Miller residence (Kalamazoo, Michigan), O. F. Miller (client)
    - Photographs, exterior (17); interior (10); negative of exterior (1); 28 items (Box 3)
    - Photographs, exterior (Oversize 2)
  - Motion Picture Association of America, office building (16th St., Washington, DC)
    - Drawings, charcoal rendering by Edward F. Chrystie (Map-case 128)
  - Morrisania housing (Bronx, New York)
    - Photographs, exterior; 14 items (Box 3)
  - Mountain Brook Country Club (Birmingham, Alabama), Miller and Martin (architects); Aymar Embury II (associate architect)
    See also Country club scrapbook and Mountain Brook Country Club scrapbook for more photographs of this building.
    - Brochure (Box 3)
    - Drawings, 1928-1929; ink on linen working drawings (8); graphite on tracing paper working drawings (40); blueprints of working drawings (5); photostats of working drawings (23); and 4 page list of revisions to drawings; 76 items (Tube 949)
    - Photographs, exterior (1); construction photographs (2) with accompanying letter; 3 items (Box 3)
    - Specifications (Box 3)
  - Museum building of the New York Botanical Gardens (Bronx, New York), Aymar Embury II and Skidmore, Owings & Merrill (architects)
    - Drawings, watercolor of front entrance (1); graphite on board perspective drawings (2); photostats of perspective drawings (10); 13 items (Oversize 10)
  - Nathaniel Hawthorne junior high school (Queens, New York)
    - Photographs, 1948; exterior; 2 items (Box 3)
  - New York Hospital, alteration (1307-1307 York Avenue, New York, New York)
    - Photographs, exterior (Box 3)
  - New York conservation exhibition, introductory building (Bronx, New York), Aymar Embury II and Harrison, Fouiloux and Abramovitz (associated architects)
    - Drawings, negative photostat of plan and elevations (Oversize 9)
  - Office and apartment buildings (Southern Pines, North Carolina), Dr. W. C. Mudgett (client)
    - Photographs, exteriors; 4 items (Box 3)
  - Oltman residence (Alpine, New Jersey), H. H. Oltman (client)
    See also Oltman residence scrapbook for more photographs of this house.
    - Photographs, exterior (6); interior (6); 12 items (Box 3)
  - Orchard Beach entrance pavilions (Bronx, New York)
    - Photographs, exterior (1); interior (1); 2 items (Box 3)
  - Palisades Trust and Guaranty Company (Englewood, New Jersey)
    - Specifications, 1906 (Box 3)
  - Park buildings (East Side Drive Park, New York, New York)
    - Photographs, exterior; 3 items (Box 3)
  - Parsons junior high school (Queens, New York)
    - Photographs, 1952; exterior (2); interior (4); and photograph of a perspective drawing (1); 7 items (Box 3)
  - Phelps residence (Caracas, Venezuela), Mr. and Mrs. William H. Phelps (client); house was also known as "La Casita"
    - Drawings, 1934-1942; graphite on tracing paper working drawings; 32 items (Tube 945)
    - Drawings, 1958; graphite on tracing paper working drawings (5); sepia diazo print working drawing (1); diazo print working drawings (4); Edward Coe Embury (architect); Aymar Embury II (consulting architect); 10 items (Tube 945)
    - Specifications, handwritten list of bath fixtures (Box 4)
  - Pomeroy residence (Englewood, New Jersey), Mrs. D. F. Pomeroy (client)
    - Drawings, 1925; graphite on tracing paper working drawings; 7 items (Tube 936)
    - Photographs, exterior (32) and excerpt from a magazine article (1); 33 items (Box 4)
    - Photographs, exterior; 2 items (Oversize 2)
  - Pomeroy residence, additions and alterations (Englewood, New Jersey)
    - Drawings, 1927; graphite on tracing paper working drawings; 7 items (Tube 936)
  - Post offices, from stock designs for President's Advisory Committee on Architecture, Embury served as the Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Architecture.. For other post office designs produced by the President's Advisory Committee on Architecture but not designed by Embury see Post offices, stock designs under Projects by other architects.
    - Brochure, Terra Cotta Company brochure (Box 4)
    - Drawings, positive photostats of plans and perspectives of typical post office designs; 21 items (Oversize 2)
    - Photographs, Beacon, New York post office (7); Englewood, Colorado post office (1); Kennett, Missouri post office (1); Newton, Illinois post office (1); Richmond, Virgnia post office (1); Salem, Illinois post office (1); South Orange, New Jersey post office (3); Southern Pines, North Carolina post office (3); unidentified post office (1); 19 items (Box 4)
  - Princeton Club of New York (New York, New York)
    See also Princeton Club scrapbook for more photographs of this building.
    - Drawings, print of drawing (Box 4)
    - Photographs, exterior(15); interior (13); 28 items (Box 4)
  - Princeton University (Princeton, New Jersey)
    - Dillon gymnasium
      - Drawings, 1944-1945; design development drawings (2); presentation drawings (5); photostats of presentation drawings (17); 24 items (Map-case 129)
      - Photographs, 1961; undated; exterior (21); interior (11); color transparencies of interior (2); photographs of drawings (3); post-fire condition of building (9); and cover of alumni magazine (1); 47 items; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Elm Club
      - Photographs, exterior (2); interior (3); 5 items (Box 4)
    - Nassau Hall
      - Drawings, graphite and colored pencil interior perspective (1); charcoal drawing (1); reproductions of drawings (6); 8 items (Oversize 10)
    - Rockefeller gymansium
      - Photographs, exterior (2); interior (1); 3 items (Box 4)
    - Student activities building
      - Photographs, photographs of drawings; 8 items (Box 4)
    - West College
      - Photographs, exterior (12); interior (1); 13 items (Box 4)
  - Prisher residence (Southern Pines, North Carolina), John Prisher (client)
    - Photographs, exterior; 3 items (Box 4)
  - Queens war memorial (Queens, New York)
    - Drawings, negative photostats of plan; 2 items (Oversize 4)
    - Drawings, watercolor renderings (2); graphite on board plans and perspectives (3); 5 items (Map-case 128)
  - Rainbow bridge (Niagara Falls, New York)
    - Drawings, negative photostats of drawings of toll booths and pedestrian entrance; 3 items (Box 4)
    - Photographs, photograph of bridge (1); photograph of drawing (1); 2 items (Box 4)
  - Richardson residence (Atlanta, Georgia), Hugh Richardson (client)
    - Photographs, exterior (26); interior (19); 45 items (Box 4)
    - Photographs, exterior (3); photographs of interior (6); 9 items (Oversize 2)
  - Roberts residence (East Hampton, Long Island, New York), Mrs. George Roberts (client)
    - Drawings, 1930; graphite on tracing paper working drawings; 18 items (Tube 950)
  - St. George's bridge (St. George's, Delaware)
    - Photographs, photographs of bridge (10); negatives (11); 21 items (Box 4)
  - Skating rink, Prospect Park (Brooklyn, New York), Embury and Lucas (architects); Aymar Embury II (consulting architect)
    - Drawings, 1951; ink on linen working drawings; 2 items (Tube 950)
  - Southern Pines Country Club (Southern Pines, North Carolina)
    - Photographs, 1923; exterior (19); postcards (4); 23 items (Box 4)
    - Photographs, 1923; exterior; 2 items (Oversize 2)
  - Strosacker Memorial Church (Midland, Michigan), Edward Coe Embury (architect); Aymar Embury II (consulting architect); Sigmond and Farkas (engineers)
    - Brochures (Box 4)
    - Photographs, exterior (9); interior (7); construction photograph (1); 17 items (Box 4)
    - Photographs, exterior (2); interior (12); photograph of plans (1); 15 items (Oversize 2)
    - Drawings, 1949-1950; VERY FRAGILE; blueprints of working drawings (27); blueprints of engineering drawings (8); sketch on butcher paper wrapper (1); 36 items (Tube 946)
    - Drawings, 1943; undated; graphite on tracing paper presentation and design development drawings; 21 items (Tube 947)
  - Teaneck public school (Teaneck, New Jersey)
    - Specifications (Box 4)
  - Tiger Inn (Princeton, New Jersey)
    - Photographs, exterior (6); interior (3); negative of exterior (1); 10 items (Box 5)
    - Photographs, exterior (Oversize 2)
  - Triborough bridge (New York, New York)
    See also Bridges scrapbooks and Lithographs of Bridges for more images of this bridge.
    - Drawings, prints of drawings; 2 items (Box 5)
    - Photographs, photographs of bridge and garage and storage facility (9); photographs of drawings (4); 13 items (Box 5)
  - Verrazano Narrows bridge, anchorage (New York, New York)
    - Drawings, November 3, 1959; diazo print by Amann and Whitney (consulting engineers) (Box 5)
    - Photographs, photograph of drawing (Box 5)
  - Way residence (Knollwood, North Carolina), Judge Way (client)
    - Photographs, exterior; 2 items (Box 5)
  - Wellington residence (Brookhaven, Long Island, New York), C. Oliver Wellington (client)
    - Photographs, exterior (6); negatives of exterior (4); 10 items (Box 5)
  - Whitestone bridge (New York, New York)
    - Drawings, graphite on tracing paper drawings (2); reproductions of drawings (8); 10 items (Oversize 5)
    - Photographs, photographs of bridge (13); negative photostat of bridge (1); photographs of toll plaza (4); construction photographs (6); photographs of drawings (3); 27 items (Box 5)
  - Wilsey residence (Englewood, New Jersey), James Wilsey (client)
    - Photographs, exterior (Box 5)
  - Winnetka Congregational church (Winnetka, Illinois), Aymar Embury II and John Leonard Hamilton (associated architects)
    See also Miscellaneous scrapbook for more photographs of this church.
    - Brochure, fundraising brochure (Box 5)
    - Drawings, 1933-1934; graphite on tracing paper design development drawings; 60 items (Tube 939)
    - Drawings, 1935; ink on linen working drawings (9); graphite on tracing paper working drawings (3); blueprints of working drawings (15); 27 items (Tube 940)
    - Photographs, exterior (2); negative of exterior (1); 3 items (Box 5)
    - Photographs, exterior (5); interior (7); reproductions of exterior photographs (2); photographs of drawings (3); 17 items (Oversize 3)
  - "Woodstock" (Southern Pines, North Carolina)
    - Photographs, exterior; 2 items (Box 5)
  - Wollman Memorial Skating Rink (New York, New York)
    - Brochure, brochure produced by the City of New York Department of Parks (Box 5)
    - Drawings, original drawing (1); reproductions of drawing (7); negative photostat of rendering (1); 9 items (Oversize 10)
    - Photographs, exterior; 5 items (Box 5)
  - Worcestor Royal Porcelain showrooms (234-236 East 46th Street, New York, New York), Wor-Kho Corporation, Mr. E. N. Khouri (President)
    - Photographs, exterior (1); interior (4); 5 items (Oversize 3)
  - World's Fair, 1939 (Queens, New York)
    See also Miscellaneous scrapbook for more photographs of the World's Fair buildings.
    - New York City building
      - Brochure, Atlantic Terra Cotta brochure; cover of The Ladle (Box 5)
      - Drawings, photostats of drawings; 25 items (Box 5)
      - Photographs, 1939; exterior (10); interior (1); photographs of model (4); construction photographs (11); 26 items (Box 5)
      - Photographs, 1939; exterior (10); interior (3); 13 items (Oversize 3)
    - State of New York amphitheater
      - Photographs, 1939; photographs of drawings; 9 items (Box 5)
  - Zenger memorial (Mt. Vernon, New York)
    - Drawings, graphite on tracing paper or board drawings; 3 items (Oversize 9)
  - Miscellaneous bridges
    - Drawings, positive and negative photostats of drawings (24); graphite on tracing paper design development drawing (1); blueprint (1); prints of renderings (6); 7 folders, 32 items (Oversize 4)
  - Miscellaneous projects
    - Drawings, negative photostat of drawing, possibly of Queens War Memorial (Box 5)
    - Drawings, negative photostats of interiors (5); graphite on tracing paper drawing (1) and negative photostat, possibly of Queens War Memorial (1); graphite on board drawing (1); charcoal drawing (1); 2 folders, 9 items (Oversize 9)
    - Photographs, exteriors (10); negatives of exteriors (4); 1 photograph of drawing (1); 15 items (Box 5)
    - Photographs, print of photographs of churches (Oversize 9)
- Projects by other architects
  In most cases, the names of these other architects are unknown.
  - Bureau of Engraving and Printing, annex (Washington, DC)
    - Photographs, construction photographs; 4 items (Box 5)
  - General Accounting Office (Washington, DC)
    - Drawings, print of drawing (Box 5)
  - Mint Museum of Art (Charlotte, North Carolina)
    - Brochure (Box 5)
    - Photographs, postcards; 4 items (Box 5)
  - Old Essex county courthouse
    - Photographs, exterior; 2 items (Box 5)
  - Post offices, stock designs for President's Advisory Committee on Architecture
    Embury served as the Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Architecture. These stock designs were produced by other architects. See also Post offices, stock designs for post offices designed by Embury.
    - Drawings, positive photostats of plans and perspectives of typical post office designs; 2 folders, 59 items (Oversize 3)
  - Tunnels and bridges, studies
    - Photographs, photographs of bridges and tunnels (7); photograph of drawing (1); 8 items (Box 5)
  - United States Government Printing Office, warehouse
    - Photographs, exterior (7); 7 items (Box 5)
  - University of Colorado (Boulder, Colorado), Charles A. Klauder (architect)
    - Drawings, June 1938; reproductions of drawings; 2 items (Oversize 3)
  - University of Delaware (Newark, Delaware), Charles A. Klauder (architect)
    - Drawings, reproductions of drawings; 3 items (Oversize 3)
    - Drawings, exterior; 2 items (Oversize 3)
  - World's Fair (Queens, New York)
    - Photographs, 1939; exterior; 13 items (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Drawings, reproduction of drawing of Henry Hudson Parkway bridge (Box 5)
    - Photographs, exteriors (9); negatives of exteriors (2); 11 items (Box 5)
- Writings by Embury
  - Articles
    - Bibliography of articles by or concerning work of Aymar Embury II (Box 5)
    - Manuscripts
      - "Articles on architectural and engineering design, vol. I" (Box 5)
      - "Articles on architectural and engineering design, vol. II and III", 2 folders (Box 6)
      - "Articles on architecture in Europe, American Colonial and Mexico" (Box 6)
      - "Book reviews" (Box 6)
      - "Military articles", includes a biographical account of Embury's service in World War I (Box 6)
    - Published
      - "Aesthetics of Bridge Design," Pencil Points, February 1938 (Box 6)
      - "Aesthetics of Concrete," Pencil Points, May 1938 (Box 6)
      - "Aesthetic Design of Steel Structures," Pencil Points, July 1938 (Box 6)
      - "Architect and the Engineer," Civil Engineering Magazine, January 1938 (Box 6)
      - "Architecture in American Country Homes," The Mentor, October 15, 1915 (Box 6)
      - "Breton Churches," Architectural Record, July 1925 (Box 6)
      - "Engineering and Architecture," Journal of the American Institute of Architects, May 1944 (Box 6)
      - "Esthetics of Bridge Design," Pencil Points, February 1938 (Box 6)
      - Esthetic Design of Steel Structures," Civil Engineering Magazine, April 1938 (Box 6)
      - "Forgotten Architectural Motif: The Moralaix Column," Architectural Record, March 1924 (Box 6)
      - "House of Tomorrow," Architecture, January 1934 (Box 6)
      - "How to Judge Architecture," House Beautiful, December 1912 (Box 6)
      - "Letter Regarding the Architectural Plan for Hofstra College", 1957 (Box 6)
      - "Plan's the Thing," Home Journal, March 1936 (Box 6)
  - Biographical Writings
    - Short stories and biographical sketches, includes autobiographical sketch (Box 6)
      See also Military articles for a biographical account of Embury's service in World War I.
- Writings on Embury
  - Articles
    - "American Airlines Hanger," Engineering New Record, July 22, 1948 (Box 6)
    - "Architects...," American Architect and Architecture, February 1938 (Box 6)
    - "Brooklyn Zoo," Architecture, January 1936 (Box 6)
    - "Charlotte Country Club," Architecture, March 1935 (Box 6)
    - "Charlotte Country Club," National Geographic Magazine (Box 6)
    - "Faculty Housing Group, Princeton, New Jersey," Architecture, August 1930 (Box 7)
    - "Filling Stations," Pencil Point, January 1941 (Box 7)
    - "Georgian Outside: A House for Luther Blake at Morristown, NJ," House and Garden, November 1936 (Box 7)
    - "House of Richard F. Hoyt, New York City," Architecture (Box 7)
    - "House of Arthur Lehman, New York City," Architecture, April 1934 (Box 7)
    - "House of O. F. Miller, Kalamazoo, MI," Architecture (Box 7)
    - Images in Moderne Bau Formen, 1911 (Box 7)
    - "Old Long Island Town Gains a Guild Hall Done in Brick," House and Garden, May 1932 (Box 7)
    - "Rebuild America," Architecture, August 1935 (Box 7)
    - "Reptiles at Bronx Zoo Move into New Quarters," Architectural Record, September 1954 (Box 7)
    - "Smiths of Wyncote, PA," Modern Living (Box 7)
    - "Some Interesting Country House Alterations" Architectural Forum (Box 7)
    - "Some Work of Aymar Embury II in the Sand Hills of North Carolina," Architectural Record, June 1924 (Box 7)
    - "Two New Community Playhouses," Architecture, March 1932 (Box 7)
    - "University Center," Princeton Alumni Weekly, October 2, 1931 (Box 7)
    - "Winnetka Congregational Church," American Architect and Architecture, October 1936 (Box 7)
    - "Work to Start at Once on $400,000 Winnetka Congregational Church," Chicago Tribune, March 31, 1935 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, includes articles from Harper's and Pencil Points (Box 7)
  - Pamphlets
    - "Bridges" (Box 7)
    - "Center for Undergrad Life at Princeton," Princeton University, 1926 (Box 7)
    - "Completion of the Henry Hudson Bridge", May 7, 1938 (Box 7)
    - "Prize Bridges 1928-1936," American Institute of Steel Construction (Box 7)
    - "Prize Bridges 1928-1937," American Institute of Steel Construction (Box 7)
- Writings on other architects
  - Articles
    - "Some Plates with Directions for Use," Pencil Points, July 1940 (Box 7)
    - "William Jensen of the Office of Aymar Embury II," Architectural Record (Box 7)